<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The anti-Quaker, or, A compendious answer to a tedious pamphlet entituled, A treatise of oaths subscribed by a jury of 12 Quakers, whose names are prefixed to it, together with the fore-man of that jury ... William Penn : alledging several reasons why they ... refuse to swear, which are refuted, and the vanity of them demonstrated both by Scripture, reason, and authority of ancient and modern writers / by Misorcus, a professed adversary of vain swearing in common discourse and communication.</title>
            <author>Misorcus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13061236</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13061236</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97025</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97025)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 406:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The anti-Quaker, or, A compendious answer to a tedious pamphlet entituled, A treatise of oaths subscribed by a jury of 12 Quakers, whose names are prefixed to it, together with the fore-man of that jury ... William Penn : alledging several reasons why they ... refuse to swear, which are refuted, and the vanity of them demonstrated both by Scripture, reason, and authority of ancient and modern writers / by Misorcus, a professed adversary of vain swearing in common discourse and communication.</title>
                  <author>Misorcus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 11-12 are stained in filmed copy. Beginning-p. 15 photographed from Huntington Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penn, William, 1644-1718. --  Treatise of oaths.</term>
               <term>Oaths.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:97025:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97025:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97025:2"/>
            <head>A Jury of 12 QUAKERS.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>William Penn,</hi> Foreman.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Alexander Parker,</item>
               <item>George Whitehead,</item>
               <item>Stephen Criſp,</item>
               <item>William Mead,</item>
               <item>Gerrard Roberts,</item>
               <item>William Welſh,</item>
               <item>Samuel Newton,</item>
               <item>Thomas Heart,</item>
               <item>John Oſgood,</item>
               <item>James Claypoole,</item>
               <item>Thomas Rudyard,</item>
               <item>Richard Richardſon.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97025:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Anti-Quaker: OR, A Compendious <hi>Anſwer</hi> to a tedious Pamphlet, Entituled, A Treatiſe of Oaths, Subſcribed By a Jury of 12 <hi>Quakers,</hi> whoſe names are prefixed to it, together with the <hi>Fore-man</hi> of that Jury, the <hi>Ring-leader</hi> of that Tribe, and Head of that Faction, <hi>William Penn,</hi> Alledging ſeveral Reaſons why they (no caſes excepted) refuſe to ſwear, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, and the Vanity of them Demonſtrated both by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Reaſon, and Authority of Ancient, and Modern Writers.</p>
            <p>By MISORCUS, A Profeſſed <hi>Adverſary</hi> of Vain <hi>Swearing</hi> in common diſcourſe, and communication.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Fear God and keep his Commandments, For this is the whole duty of man,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 12.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God: him ſhalt thou ſerve, and cleave unto him, and ſwear by his Name,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 10.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to his moſt Sacred Majeſty, at the Angel in <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97025:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97025:3"/>
            <head>TO The moſt Judicious View of the Right Honourable the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the High Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</head>
            <p>THE unworthy Author moſt Humbly preſents the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> as the 13 Head-Quakers did of late moſt boldly dedicate their's, <hi>Subſcrib'd</hi> by them <hi>on the behalf of the reſt of their Friends</hi> (they are their own words) with an earneſt ſupplicate to be freed from the impoſition of all Oaths, which <hi>for pure conſcience
<pb facs="tcp:97025:4"/>ſake</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>they cannot take at all,</hi> concealing (what is their main drift) their deſire to obtain a free uſe for the future of their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Meetings, or <hi>Conventicles,</hi> the <hi>Seed-plots</hi> of faction, and ſeditious practiſes, as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> proves at large in divers Epiſtles to the then Raigning Emperours, againſt the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> (the <hi>Quakers</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors) commending to them by way of advice this moderate <hi>State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maxime, Doctrina præcedat, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plina ſequatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With reſpect to the former part of it I have (as many of my <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> in the Miniſtry have learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done before me) imployed my weak endeavours for the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſcrupulous Conſciences, referring the execution of the latter
<pb facs="tcp:97025:4"/>part of it, for ſevere<note n="*" place="margin">Corrigi eos cupimus non necari, nee Diſciplinam circa eos neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligi. <hi>Aug. Ep. 127.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> to your <hi>Honours</hi> great Authority, and moſt Sage Counſels; for a bleſſing on which, <hi>to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods glory, the good of the Church, the ſafety, honour and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of our Soveraign and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> with the publick you have the daily private Prayers and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of him who conceales his <hi>Name,</hi> not out of a guilty Fear, but a cautious Prudence, not willing to have it aſpers'd with reproaches and unjuſt calumnies, with bitter railings and Invectives, againſt which there is no fence from the moſt unſpotted Innocence, and wherewith they uſually beſpatter thoſe who diſſent from them in their vain, falſe, and Antiſcriptural opinions, which they cannot main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain either by Gods holy Word,
<pb facs="tcp:97025:5"/>or any rational Arguments, as I ſhall (God aſſiſting me) Prove, and Illuſtrate in the following Treatiſe, preſented in all Humility to your <hi>Honours</hi> for its Patronage, not doubting of your gracious par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for the boldneſs of my Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97025:5"/>
            <head>THE REFUTER'S Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is a Generation</hi> (ſayes <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 30.12.) <hi>that are pure in their own eyes, and yet are not waſhed from their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs;</hi> a ſort of men that <hi>walk after the Fleſh in the luſt of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, and deſpiſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, preſumptuous, ſelf-willed, and that are not afraid to ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> (or thoſe that are ſet over them by God to be their Rulers and Governours) 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. yet, being ſwell'd with a Tympany of Pride, are admirers of themſelves, even to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of others. I heartily wiſh, for their Souls ſake, that this Character of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> might not juſtly be appropriated to ſome of the <hi>People cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97025:6"/>Quakers,</hi> who refuſe to Swear, and will not be tied to the diſcharge of their Duties by Oaths mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto them by Subordinate Magiſtrates, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they deſerve to be move properly called (as they are indeed) <hi>Anabaptiſts; Quo genere hominum nullum aut pertinacius aut arrogantius, aut in erroribus aut figmentis feracius,</hi> ſo the judicious <hi>Cramerus</hi> in his third Claſſis of Hereticks, <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Than whom no kind of men are more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacious and arrogant, and more pregnant in the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating of falſe and erroneous Opinions;</hi> of which (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt divers others) this is one, <hi>That it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to Swear in any caſe whatſoever:</hi> and this opinion they ground upon our Saviours Precept or Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34. The proper ſenſe and meaning of which Precept when I have fully demonſtrated, both from the <hi>occaſion</hi> of his delivering it, and from the <hi>ſcope</hi> or <hi>intention</hi> of it; confirming my Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the joynt conſent of the beſt Interpreters, alſo by the ſtrength of divers weighty Reaſons; it will appear to all judicious Readers, that the foreſaid Tenet is both abſurd, falſe, and frivolous; and that all their numerous Allegations or Teſtimonies to the contrary (which are no fewer than 207.) out of the Writings of <hi>Gentiles, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> are to little or no purpoſe, of no validity to maintain the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker's Theſis</hi> or <hi>Poſition,</hi> in regard that moſt of them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inveigh againſt Perjury and ordinary or common Swearing in our familiar Diſcourſes, which was chiefly intended (as it ſhall be evidently proved) by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Prohibition, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> Upon the <hi>rind</hi> or <hi>ſhell</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Letter) of which words the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med feed ſo much, and gnaw the <hi>Bone,</hi> that they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97025:6"/>never come at the <hi>Kernel</hi> and <hi>Marrow,</hi> or true <hi>mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed to the explication of this <hi>prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Precept, I muſt take leave to commend to the view of the people that go under the name of <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> (or rather to the Pen-men of that <hi>Treatiſe</hi>) a Saying of a Chriſtian Divine Philoſopher;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Athenag.</hi> l. de Reſurrectione.</note> 
               <hi>There was never any Truth, though ratified by the Authoritie of God's Word, which had not a Lye for its Attendant;</hi> which muſt not be ſo underſtood, as if <hi>Truth</hi> were the natural Parent of a <hi>Lye;</hi> but in regard of the malice and perverſeneſs of men who did darken it with their miſty Gloſſes, and corrupt it by their wreſting of it, with falſe Interpretations. Thus the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> like many in our Dayes, had learned this Art of ſpreading and maintaining their falſe Doctrine, by corrupting the Sacred Text. For, whereas God, commanding us to have in due and awful Reverence his holy Name, forbade the <hi>Jews,</hi> and in them us Chriſtians, to <hi>take the ſame in vain,</hi> Exod. 20.7. <hi>i. e.</hi> to take it into our mouths idly, or to no purpoſe, without any warrant from Neceſſity, and without reſpect to the advance of his Glory; the <hi>Scribes</hi> or Doctors of the Law expounding <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in vain,</hi> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>falſly,</hi> i. e. to back and confirm a Lye, which word we find, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.12. <hi>Thou ſhalt not Swear by my name falſly;</hi> they hereby confounded two diſtinct Precepts. For, by the later in <hi>Leviticus</hi> is forbidden Perjury, which is the confirmation of a Lye by an Oath: by the former Precept in <hi>Exodus</hi> all vain, inconſiderate and raſh Oaths, which men commonly uſe to confirm or ratifie the Truth in their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97025:7"/>private Negotiations, Contracts, Bargainings, and Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>From this falſe Gloſs of the <hi>Scribes</hi> interpreting the Third Commandment, as if only <hi>Perjury</hi> were forbid by it, and this too only in the abuſe of God's Sacred <hi>Name;</hi> from this corrupt Spring iſſued theſe three perverſe and depraved Doctrines, which in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's time were ſetled in the minds and hearts of the deluded Jews.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to Swear by the <hi>Creature,</hi> and to forſwear, they affirmed to be no ſin.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they counted it no breach of the Third Commmandment, if they uſed in their ordinary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe the <hi>Name</hi> of God, ſo long as they did what they promiſed, and affirmed what was true. With the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> in this Second Opinion agree both <hi>Maldonat</hi> on <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. and <hi>Socinus</hi> with his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, from this later impure Stream or Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on iſſued another, as corrupt and unſound; it was this, That whatſoever they had bound themſelves to by an Oath in the Name of God, they were obliged to do it, were the thing never ſo unjuſt and bad.</p>
            <p>Our bleſſed Saviour, as it did become ſo wiſe a Teacher <hi>who came from God,</hi> as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. intending and endeavouring to root out of the peoples minds theſe <hi>Phariſaical</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, or Principles unſound in themſelves, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of an holy Life or good Manners, in his Firſt Sermon <hi>Ad populum</hi> on the Mount, gave them all, as it were, their deaths Wound, ſtifled and choak'd them with one general Precept or Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtrengthened with Divine Authority, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97025:7"/>of his own Perſon, <hi>But I ſay unto you, Swear not at all;</hi> i.e. <hi>Swear not at all per ullam rem creatam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beza in L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. Ex proximè ſequentibus quas Chriſtus damnat for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulis liquet, non ipſum ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jurandum reprehendi.</note> by any thing created, or which is the Workmanſhip of God, for by ſo doing you will attract to your ſelves the guilt of Idolatrie, by aſcribing to the Creature that which is proper and eſſential to the Creatour, i. e. <hi>omniſciency,</hi> and <hi>omnipotency,</hi> as if it knew our hearts and ſecret intentions, and could puniſh us if we ſhould be guilty of Perjury. With the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Beza</hi> in the Margine concurrs his Compatriot, and no leſs Learned <hi>Calvin</hi> in his Comment on the Text, whoſe aſſertion is this, <hi>Particula</hi> omninò <hi>non ad</hi> jurandi <hi>Verbum refertur, ſed ad ſubject as Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum formulas,</hi> i.e. <hi>The Particle</hi> At all <hi>is to be referred not to the words which go before</hi> Swear not, <hi>but to that which follows, Neither by</hi> Heaven— <hi>nor by the</hi> Earth— <hi>neither by</hi> Hieruſalem— <hi>nor by thy</hi> Head— By this our Saviour gave a check to the Scribes firſt Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> That to Swear by the Creature was no ſin.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as this Prohibition, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the <hi>Creatures,</hi> be they the holy <hi>Evangeliſts, Saints</hi> departed, or <hi>Angels,</hi> (whom to invocate, as in Prayer, ſo in Swearing, is held to be lawful by the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> as it was by the <hi>Manichees:</hi>)<note place="margin">Epiphan l. 1. c. 19.</note> ſo it includes and forbids all vain and ſuperfluous Oaths in uſe then among the Jews, and now too frequently uſed by Chriſtians in their common and familiar Diſcourſes. That this was likewiſe our bleſſed Saviours meaning, may be evidenced by that which follows by way of Precept after the Prohibition,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 37.</note> 
               <hi>But let your communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be Yea, Yea, and Nay, Nay,</hi> i.e. In your common talk and diſcourſe uſe only a bare <hi>Affirmation</hi> of what you know to be true, and a ſimple <hi>Negation</hi> of what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97025:8"/>you are aſſured is falſe, without interpoſing the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Sacred Name of God. <hi>Let your communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be Yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quod dicis verbo dic o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, quod ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas verbo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li confirmare facto. <hi>Ugo.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Yea,</hi> &amp;c. On which words <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>go</hi> thus Gloſſes, <hi>Let not thy actions give thy words the Lye: what thou haſt affirmed or promiſed with thy tongue, ratifie the ſame by thy action: and what thou haſt denied in thy words, confirm not the ſame by thy deeds.</hi> This Gloſs is inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and might be embraced, if Chriſt had ſaid on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Let your Yea be Yea,</hi> &amp;c. but theſe words, <hi>Let your communication</hi>— being prefixed to the <hi>Yea, Yea,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and require another (and that more proper) inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, which may be this,<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>za.</note> Becauſe men uſually ſwear, that, what they affirm or deny, may be fully credited or believed; our bleſſed Lord therefore commands us rather to uſe a double Affirmation, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Yea, Yea;</hi> and a double Negation, <hi>Nay, Nay,</hi> than raſhly ſwear by Gods holy <hi>Name:</hi> By which to ſwear (and that in their familiar diſcourſes) the Jews in our Saviours time thought it (as was ſaid before) lawful, (and ſo they had been taught by the Scribes) in caſe the thing was true which they had ſworn. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as they deemed it not to be Perjury (or thought they were not perjured) if they had Sworn only by the Creatures and broke their Oath, miſinterpreting that Text, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform unto the Lord thine Oaths:</hi> Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our for theſe reaſons (and this was the ſcope only, or intent of his Prohibition) ſaid unto them, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> Swear not by the <hi>Creature</hi> (to do this is <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious</hi> and <hi>idolatrous.</hi>) Swear not <hi>raſhly</hi> nor <hi>lightly;</hi> this is <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>blaſphemous.</hi> Swear not <hi>falſly;</hi> this is to back a Lye with an Oath, upon which follows the guilt of Perjury. Laſtly, Swear not <hi>unjuſtly,</hi> bind
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97025:8"/>not your ſelf by an Oath to do what is againſt the rule of Juſtice or Honeſty; by this you make an Oath to be <hi>Iniquitatis vinculum,</hi> a bond of Iniquity, which is rather to be broken with repentance and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of heart for taking of it, than kept. Such was <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi>'s raſh Oath to the wanton Daughter of <hi>Herodias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 6.23.</note> to give unto her whatſoever ſhe ſhould ask: Such was that of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who bound themſelves under a Curſe, ſaying, <hi>That they would neither eat nor drink,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 23.14.</note> 
               <hi>till they had killed Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Prohibition</hi> of Chriſt being thus explained, (for which I have the conſent of the moſt and beſt Interpreters, both modern and ancient, whoſe names are ſo numerous, that the Margine cannot contain them) to that Explication I ſhall ſubjoyn many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable and weighty Reaſons, to evince and prove the falſity and abſurdity of the <hi>Anabaptiſt's Tenet,</hi> or <hi>Theſis</hi> (which is grounded upon that general <hi>Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>) <hi>That in any caſe whatſoever it is not lawful for a Chriſtian to ſwear.</hi> For the diſproving, and refuting of which dangerous Poſition (and that I may reconcile <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> to the <hi>Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6.13. 10 20. Iſa. 65.16. Ierem. 12.16.</note> many Texts in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> and in the <hi>Prophets,</hi> which enjoyn us to <hi>Swear</hi> by the Name of God, to the prohibitive com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of our Saviour) let me premiſe this for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Maxime or Theſis, <hi>That the Precepts of the Goſpel are not repugnant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Præcepta E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelii non contrariantur præceptis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or contrary to the Commands of the Law.</hi> This Poſition is defended and proved at large by S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Nineteenth Book againſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the Heretick, <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. What the Law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, the Goſpel does not forbid; and what the one forbids, the other does not allow: but both meet together in a ſweet conſent and harmony of Truth,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97025:9"/>and (as it were) kiſs and embrace each other; ſo that the Goſpel in a manner beſpeaks the Law in the words of that <hi>Paraſitical</hi> Servant in the <hi>Comedie</hi> to his Maſter, <hi>Quod ais aio, quod negas nego,</hi> what you command I commend, what you condemn I diſallow: and there is no ſurer or better way of expounding the Law than by the Goſpel, and of the Goſpel than by the Law, according to that known ſaying of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>næus,</hi> l. 4. c. 63. <hi>Secundùm Scripturas expoſitio legitima eſt, &amp; ſine periculo, It is the ſafeſt courſe and method for the ending of Diſputes, to expound Scripture by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, one Text by another, if there be a ſeeming diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the former from the later.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I muſt put this Queſtion to a diſſenting <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> to any one of the People ſo called, Doſt thou imagine, or dareſt thou ſay, that <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets borrowed not their Light of Revelation or Doctrine from Chriſt the everlaſting <hi>Sun</hi> of <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> (who likewiſe being the Eternal <hi>Word</hi> of God,<note place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> ſpake to them by his Spirit, and dictated to them what we find in their Writings, as Rules of our Faith and Manners?) I preſume thou wilt not ſay it; and unleſs thou wilt aſſert, that they were not true <hi>Stars,</hi> but only ſlimie <hi>Meleors</hi> coloured with ſhews and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Truth, and that their Doctrine is falſe; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thou aſſert this (which is an horrid and hainous crime, even blaſphemy, but to think) and I know thou wilt not, then thou muſt ſet thy Seal to this undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Truth, that in ſome caſes it is not unlawful or ſinful to uſe an <hi>Oath,</hi> according to that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in his Exhortation to revolted <hi>Iſrael, Thou ſhalt ſwear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord liveth, in Truth, in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in Righteouſneſs.</hi> i. e. When thou makeſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97025:9"/>or takeſt an Oath,<note place="margin">Iudicio caret juramentum incautum, veritate ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentum mendax, Iuſtitia jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum &amp; illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citum. Aquin.</note> thou ſhalt ſwear by the Eternal Lord of Life, who is a diſcerner of the mind and heart, to whom are clearly known the inward moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it, who will likewiſe ſeverely puniſh us if we be falſe in our ſayings, and unjuſt in our doings. This profeſſion we make when we invocate him in taking of an Oath, being called to it by the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and hereby God's name is ſanctified, (it being an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary part of God's worſhip) but with this <hi>proviſo,</hi> That the three forenamed Cautions or Circumſtances mentioned before by the <hi>Prophet</hi> do attend it. They that thus Swear by Gods Name <hi>ſhall be commended,</hi> Pſal. 63.12. <hi>i.e.</hi> They that ſwear in weighty matters (when they are urged to it) either for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Truth, or to maintain their ſuſpected In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and oblige themſelves by an Oath before a Magiſtrate to do that which is righteous, juſt, honeſt, and good; ſuch men ſin not, neither offend againſt our <hi>Saviour's,</hi> or S. <hi>James</hi> his Prohibition, <hi>Swear not,</hi> chap. 5.12. by which is condemned and forbid only raſh and inconſiderate, falſe and diſhoneſt <hi>Swearing,</hi> approved not of by the Laws of men, and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Word of God, by which the contrary is commended, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.16. <hi>He that Sweareth in the earth ſhall Swear by the God of Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To my former Poſition and Queſtion propoſed to a Scrupulous <hi>Quaker</hi> (or rather <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi>) I ſhall add another <hi>Quære,</hi> which I deſire him to conſider; it is this, Whether Chriſt's Aſſertion and Teſtimony of Himſelf be not true, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.17. <hi>I came not to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfil it.</hi> I cannot expect, if I ſhould talk with him, but that he would ſay in his proper Language, <hi>Yea.</hi> This being granted (as he dares not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97025:10"/>deny it) then I would reply, and tell him, That if Chriſt came <hi>not to deſtroy the Law,</hi> then he forbade not what the Law commands; and if he came to <hi>fulfil it,</hi> then he muſt acknowledge that Chriſt did that for which he came into the World (for his coming was not in vain, or fruitleſs) and that He (<hi>in whom dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the fulneſs of tine Godhead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.9</note> i.e. who is perfect God and man in one perſon, and in whom there is a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Wiſdom and all heavenly Grace) <hi>fulfilled</hi> the Law two manner of ways,<note place="margin">Aquin. 12.101. Q. 2. Art</note> 
               <hi>opere &amp; ore,</hi> by his <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Words,</hi> or Divine Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> by his Works or Deeds, in that, to leave us an Example of a meek heart and ſound obedience, he ſubmitted himſelf to the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> Law, being cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcis'd the Eighth day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So likewiſe to ſatisfie the rigour of God's Juſtice, he fully performed the <hi>Moral</hi> by his <hi>Active</hi> obedience, doing what the Lord required of us to be done, thereby to bring us to Heaven; and by his <hi>Paſſive,</hi> ſuffering for our Sins to redeem us from the pains and torments of Hell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Verum legis ſenſum expti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo.</note>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> he fulfilled the Law by his heavenly <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;</hi> this he did by explaining the full ſcope, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or meaning of the Law (as in thoſe two Caſes of <hi>Murder</hi> and <hi>Adultery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Præcepta le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis ordinando ut tutiùs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervaretur quod lex ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuer at. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin.</note> Matth. 5.21, 27.) and by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing Rules for the better obſerving of the Laws <hi>Affirmative</hi> and <hi>Negative</hi> commands.</p>
            <p>Thus becauſe the Law forbids all kinds of <hi>Perjury, Thou ſhalt not Swear by my Name falſly,</hi> Lev. 6.5. that this <hi>Prohibition</hi> might be the better kept and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and men ſecured from the danger of ſo great a ſin (in regard that men accuſtomed to Swearing, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Perjury</hi> but a light and frivolous thing) Chriſt therefore in his Sermon upon the Mount, gave to his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97025:10"/>Auditors or Diſciples a ſafe and wholſom admonition, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> i.e. never, <hi>niſi in causâ neceſſitatis</hi> (as the Learned <hi>Zanchy</hi> upon that Text) except in caſes of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi gloria Domini vindicanda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>t fratris ædifca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio promovenda,</hi> when and where the glory of God is to be vindicated by a bold defence of the Truth oppoſed, and when our neighbours welfare may thereby be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted, and either our own credit or reputation preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> himſelf (who was a rigid enemy to <hi>Swearing</hi> (i.e. to vain and idle <hi>Oaths</hi> in mutual and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conference) and in whoſe miſtaken and wreſted Sayings the Pen-man of the <hi>Treatiſe againſt Oaths</hi> does much <note n="*" place="margin">The Author has ſtuff'd two and twenty Pages in his Treatiſe with Citati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of that moſt Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Father, which are nothing to his purpoſe; for S. Chryſoſtome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not all kinde of Swearing.</note> triumph) he in his Fifth Homily <hi>Ad pop. Antioch.</hi> does clearly admit of, or allow an Oath to be taken in a caſe of Neceſſity, as is evident by theſe words, (cited in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, <hi>p.</hi> 72. of the treatiſe) <q>
                  <hi>Moreover, this I ſay, That in the mean time we may cut off Superfluous Oaths, thoſe I mean, which are made raſhly amongst Friends and Servants without any Neceſſity,</hi> &amp;c.</q> Hence I inferr (having great and weighty Reaſons which hereafter I ſhall produce, and that florid golden mouth Father's warrant for my Aſſertion,)<note place="margin">Neceſſitas tollit ferias. Prov. Heb.</note> That as <hi>Neceſſity</hi> (as we ſay commonly) has no Law; ſo to take an <hi>Oath</hi> when a man is neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated or compelled to take it, is not ſuperfluous, vain, or ſinful, and no violation of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Precept, or of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law, I mean the Third Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain:</hi> For if every <hi>Negative</hi> Precept does include (which no man will deny) the contrary to it, which is the <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative,</hi> we may then inferre, and ſay with <hi>Moſes</hi> (who ſpake from God) <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6.13.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97025:11"/>
               <hi>God, and ſerve him, and ſhalt Swear by his Name, not vainly,</hi> or to no purpoſe, but to juſtifie the Truth, or to give to thy Neighbour (who requires it) an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thy integrity, or ſincerity of thy promiſe; and in other caſes which are warranted by an inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Neceſſity.</hi> Thus if any one ſhould accuſe thee of perfidiouſneſs or ſlander, as having with the black tooth of Calumny wounded his reputation, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded him of his goods; If thou, to purge thy ſelf from this foul aſperſion, ſhalt deny the fact by a ſimple and bare proteſtation of thy innocency, and he ſtill ſuſpecting thee to the contrary ſhall require an <hi>Oath</hi> of thee, to confirm his belief of what thou denieſt; in ſuch a caſe, to vindicate thy credit, and to work out of his mind that injurious ſuſpicion, thou mayeſt uſe a ſolemn <hi>Atteſtation,</hi> by invocating or calling God to witneſs the Truth of thy Aſſertion. And that in ſuch or the like caſe (to ſettle in another a perſwaſion of our Integrity) an <hi>Oath</hi> between private perſons is no ſin; we have the examples of God's Saints in the holy Scriptures to warrant it,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.23, 24.</note> as that of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing urged to it by <hi>Abimelech</hi> King of <hi>Gerar,</hi> did Swear unto him that he would not deal falſly with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The like <hi>promiſſory</hi> Oath paſſed between <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Laban, Gen.</hi> 31.53. and from <hi>Boaz</hi> to <hi>Ruth,</hi> Chap. 3.13. Let me annex to theſe Examples the teſtimony of Saint <hi>Auguſtine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. l. 10. de Serm Dom c. 30.</note> When Chriſt (ſayes he) enjoyned us to uſe in our common diſcourſe, by way of Affirmation and Negation, <hi>Yea, Yea, Nay, Nay,</hi> He ſaid not that whatſoever is more than this is evil or ſin, but <hi>proceeds from evil,</hi> i.e. <hi>from ſome bad principle, from the evil of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity</hi> in him, who requires an Oath, and that is his <hi>incredulity,</hi> ſuſpecting the Truth of the others Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97025:11"/>or Report, or his want of <hi>Charity,</hi> entertaining in his breaſt a bad opinion of his Brother, and perhaps undeſervedly; <hi>Tu enim non malè facis qui benè uteris juratione,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For thou doeſt not ill who uſeſt an Oath well</hi> (i. e. to a good end) <hi>that thou mayeſt beget in another a firm belief of the Truth, and of thy ſincerity: He rather doeth ill whoſe diffidence or diſtruſt enforces thee to uſe an Oath; his ſin ſhall not be imputed to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the farther ratification of my former <hi>Poſition</hi> concerning an <hi>Oath's</hi> legality, in caſe of an undeniable and inevitable <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> I ſhall propound one <hi>Quære</hi> more to <hi>W. P.</hi> the Quakers Oracle or Anteſignanus of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> it is this; Suppoſe a knot of Thieves ſhould aſſault thee in thy journey, and, having by force and violence robbed thee of thy money, ſhould urge thee to Swear that thou wilt not betray nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them by raiſing the Country to a purſuit of them, in the mean time affrighting thee with execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dreadful Oaths, that unleſs thou ſecure them by a ſolemn <hi>Oath,</hi> they will kill thee; tell me, <hi>W.P.</hi> wouldſt thou in this caſe rather loſe thy life than <hi>Swear,</hi> to which by blaſphemous threats they urge thee? I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe, that, as thou haſt a plentiful Eſtate, thou wouldſt not eaſily part with it, and thy life at once, by fondly bogling at an innocent Oath: This perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I have of thee, becauſe, as thou profeſſeſt thy ſelf, with the reſt of thy Gang, to be <hi>men</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Sanctity, ſo I conceive that thou haſt not wholly forfeited thy Reaſon, but by that ſparkling Light which ſtill remains in it, thou (being caſt into theſe ſtreights) wil'ſt conſider, <hi>Firſt,</hi> that it thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeſt to <hi>Swear,</hi> thou ſhalt run upon the rock of a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous guilt, which is the breach of the Sixth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97025:12"/>by which the uſe of all lawful means for the preſervation of our lives is commanded; and if we may preſerve them and will not by ſuch means, we are ſelf-murderers. Now <hi>Swearing</hi> is not abſolutely forbid neither by Chriſt nor his Apoſtles. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thou ſurely wouldſt conſider, that by thy refuſing to Swear, thou ſhouldſt be the occaſion, or rather the partial cauſe of the loſs of thy Brother's Soul (a Thief by the bond of Nature is thy Brother) he being made guilty of Murther by ſhedding thy blood, which might be kept in thy veins by thy taking of that harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Oath,</hi> the which being once taken, muſt be religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly kept, for that he that is robbed is bound to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and not to betray a Thief, having Sworn not to do it; ſo the late moſt Pious and Learned Biſhop of <hi>Norwich</hi> determines the Caſe,<note place="margin">Caſ. Conſc. Reſol. Dec. 1. c. 8.</note> and annexes this ſaying to his determination, (to deterre all men from <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury,</hi> or breaking their Oaths) <hi>When once we have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed God in any buſineſs, it is dangerous not to be punctual in the performance.</hi> With him concurres in the ſame opinion the profound Doctor <hi>Sanderſon</hi> in his Fifth Lecture and Seventeenth Section,<note place="margin">Lib. de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram. obligat.</note> where he diſputes the caſe againſt <hi>Baldwin,</hi> once Profeſſor of Divinity at <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> and having anſwered his three Arguments alledged to the contrary, concludes, That as it is not unlawful for one to Swear to a Thief (ſuppoſing that if he did not, he ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be murder'd) ſo there lies a neceſſity upon him of keeping that <hi>Oath</hi> not to diſcover him to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, <hi>Si licuit jurare, licebit &amp; juramentum obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> they are his very words, <hi>pag.</hi> 132. So are not thoſe cited out of his 141. <hi>page</hi> by the falſifying Penner of the <hi>Treatiſe;</hi> I muſt therefore be bold to tell that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97025:12"/>man of Truth that he is guilty of <hi>Forgery,</hi> I might rather ſay in plainer and more expreſs terms, of a <hi>Lye,</hi> to which the Thirteen Abettors of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe have ſubſcribed, as they have to many more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in that Treatiſe, (as ſhall hereafter be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced.) The Author (or rather Authors of it, for no doubt many hands and Jeſuited cunning Heads con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd to the compoſing of it) having aſſerted <hi>every Oath to be vain and unlawful,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 20.</note> (under which notion the Oath of <hi>Supremacy.</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> muſt needs fall in his opinion) gives this reaſon of his Aſſertion, <hi>For Chriſt's Prohibition,</hi> Swear not at all, <hi>was not a meer Repetition of what was forbidden under the Law, but what the Law allowed, as Biſhop</hi> Sanderſon <hi>well obſerveth, in theſe words,<note place="margin">There is not one Syllable to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in that Page 141. of the Book Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1647.</note> 
               </hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>It was not needful that Chriſt ſhould forbid what was forbidden in it ſelf, or was alwayes unlawful, which vain Swearing was and is by the Third Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Thou ſhalt not take, &amp;c. <hi>Therefore Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Prohibition of the Law,</hi> i.e. <hi>condemned all kind of Swearing.</hi>
               </q> This fallacious way of arguing, by making Authors ſpeak what they never ſaid nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and by drawing concluſions from premiſes miſinterpreted, has a great ſmack and tang of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite.</hi> But to the whole I anſwer thus <hi>partim,</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; firſt I deny the truth of the Aſſertion, <hi>Every Oath, &amp;c.</hi> and the Reaſon he give for it I affirm to be invalid and falſe, <hi>For Chriſt's Prohibition, &amp;c.</hi> In op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Reaſon, Firſt, I ſhall lay down this <hi>Theſis</hi> or Poſition, That Chriſt by his Precept or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitive Command repeated (and that he uſually did) what was forbid by the Law, ſuch is <hi>vain Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>Swearing</hi> by any thing but by the Name of God in weighty cauſes, and in caſes of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97025:13"/>we are commanded by the Authority of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. Secondly, I affirm that it was needful and very expedient Chriſt ſhould do it (as it was for Saint <hi>Paul to write the ſame things to the Philippians,</hi> chap. 3.1.) and that, <hi>Firſt,</hi> by reaſon of the perverſeneſs, dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſtupidity, and forgetfulneſs of mans nature, which needs <hi>Line upon Line,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 28.13.</note> 
               <hi>Precept upon Precept,</hi> that is, to have the ſame Commands and Prohibitions oft repeated, and inculcated. <hi>Secondly,</hi> it was needful and very convenient, that thereby he might ſhew that there was an amicable harmony or agreement between the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and the <hi>Law,</hi> ſo that what was enjoyned and commanded by the former, is not forbid and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the later. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it was needful that ſo he might gain an higher eſtimate to the <hi>Law of Moſes,</hi> by not contradicting or gainſaying of its Precepts, but ratifying the ſame by his Commands, he being greater than <hi>Moſes,</hi> who received thoſe lively Oracles from his mouth on the Mount. And, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> he might do it (<hi>i.e.</hi> repeat the ſame Commands which were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by <hi>Moſes</hi>) to refute and give a check to thoſe blaſphemous conceits (which he foreſaw would ſpring up in the Church in after Ages) or to thoſe groſs opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the <hi>Manichees</hi> and of their followers, who maintained that there were two Deities, the one Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Old Law,</hi> the other of the <hi>New,</hi> which are at large confuted by the <hi>Malleus Hæreticorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom 6:</note> Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Tractates againſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the Manichean, and his Abettors, <hi>Adimantus, Fortunatus, Secundinus,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>From all that has been ſaid, and for theſe four Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons I inferre, that the forenamed Author is guilty of no leſs a ſin than <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> by aſſerting,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>That Chriſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97025:13"/>forbade what the Law allowed, and in the room of ſuch Oaths and Vows as were to be performed unto the Lord, he introduced</hi> Yea <hi>and</hi> Nay <hi>with a moſt abſolute</hi> Swear not at all. What is this but to make our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour (who ſpake by the Prophets) to contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by commanding one thing in the Law, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thing in the Goſpel, or by forbidding what he had commanded; as if he (who is unchangeable, and whoſe <hi>Precepts</hi> as well as his <hi>Promiſes</hi> are <hi>Yea and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.20.</note> i. e. immutable) had upon better thoughts alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his mind or judgement? To think this, much more to ſay it, is blaſphemous. The Author of the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe</hi> does in effect ſay as much, by affirming that all Oaths, in their full compaſs and latitude, are by Chriſt's <hi>Swear not at all</hi> prohibited: witneſs his bold Proteſtation, which he makes in his own, and in the name of all his Brethren,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 155.</note> 
               <hi>We profeſs our ſelves in the Fear of Almighty God, to be ſuch, as have thus learned Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and for the Reverence we bear to his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Commandment, we can't take an Oath in any Caſe.</hi> He ſhould have ſaid, we will not take God's Name in vain; for this in part is the ſenſe and meaning of Chriſt's command, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> (with his Confederates) bears ſuch a Reverence to God's Commandments, why then does he (or how dares he) ſo audaciouſly and openly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs againſt Three of them at once? I mean the Fifth, Sixth, and the Ninth, <hi>Honour thy Father, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt do no Murder. Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Neighbour.</hi> This he has done by wounding the reputation of a moſt righteous and Learned Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> a renown'd Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Church, now a glorious Saint in Heaven;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97025:14"/>and by belying him, and that by atteſting he wrote that which he never did (for that I cannot find any ſuch thing or words in his moſt elaborate Work <hi>De juramenti Obligatione</hi>) and is diametrically oppoſite, or contrary to his known opinion, and the whole frame of his Book. The words which the Father of Lyes put into the <hi>Treatiſt</hi>'s mouth, and from thence dropt into his erring Pen, are theſe, <hi>Chriſt exceeded the Prohibition of the Law,</hi> i. e. condemned all kind of Swearing. Can any believe that ſo wiſe, ſo godly, and acute perſon did ever ſay or write this, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by contradict himſelf; who, for the preventing of <hi>Perjury,</hi> has preſcribed in that golden Book many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Rules for the right taking of an <hi>Oath,</hi> whether it be <hi>Aſſertory</hi> or <hi>Promiſſory,</hi> and defines an Oath thus, <hi>Eſt actus religioſus in quo ad confirmandam rem dubiam Deus teſtis invocatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>A religious act in which</hi> (or by which) <hi>for the confirmation of a thing in doubt</hi> (or called into queſtion, it being uncertain) <hi>God is invocated</hi> (or called upon) <hi>to be a witneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it is a religious Act he proves, <hi>Firſt,</hi> by the Authority of the Scriptures,<note n="*" place="margin">From hence the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men aver that it is <hi>Actu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>æ,</hi> or of that worſhip which is only due to God. Aquin. 22. Q. 89.</note> 
               <hi>Deuter.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him, and Swear by his Name. Secondly,</hi> from the joynt conſent of all <hi>Nations,</hi> who although they were only led by the dim light of Nature, did account of an <hi>Oath</hi> as a moſt Sacred thing, and ſo in their Writings is oft termed a <hi>Sacrament.</hi> He proves it, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> from moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and clear Reaſon, becauſe an <hi>Oath</hi> tends or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces much to God's honour, and to the glory of his Name, by the acknowledgment or confeſſion of his <hi>Truth, Knowledge, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Almighty Power;</hi> all theſe four Attributes we acknowledge to be in him, when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97025:14"/>in taking of an <hi>Oath</hi> we call upon him to be out wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Judge. What can the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> anſwer to this? how can he vindicate himſelf from the guilt of notorious falſity and forgery, by averring that the Biſhop aſſerted, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> by his prohibitive Precept <hi>exceeded the Prohibition of the Law,</hi> or <hi>Third Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> by commanding us not only not to Swear vainly or falſly, but not to uſe an Oath in any caſe whatſoever. Does not that godly <hi>Prelate</hi> in his Tenth Section of his Seventh <hi>Prælection</hi> lay this down for an undeniable concluſion, <hi>Juramenti uſus eſt licitus,</hi> and proves an Oath to be lawful, as by divers weighty Reaſons, drawn from the uſe of it in the Old and New Teſtament, for that the <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1.9. Gal. 1.20. Gen. 14.22.26.31.31.53.</note> Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Patriarchs</hi> did uſe it, and all Controverſies were appointed by <hi>Moſes</hi> to be terminated or ended by it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.11. ſo alſo from the Conditions to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Swearing preſcribed by the Prophets, as in that fourth Chapter of <hi>Jerem.</hi> verſ. 2. which I have formerly cited and illuſtrated; after all which he challenges any man to give juſt Reaſon, why under the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> it ſhould be lawful for holy men to Swear, and not for the Faithful under the <hi>New,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this act of Swearing did not appertain to the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law,</hi> which was abrogated by Chriſt, as is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident by the end of it (which is of perpetual uſe) and that is the confirmation of the Truth, and ending all litigious Diſputes and ſtrifes about it. And will not any prudent man conclude from all this, that an Oath to its own and proper nature, is not an evil thing, but lawful and good, when much hurt and many diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances which may happen in the tranſaction of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affairs, may by it be prevented? This is atteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97025:15"/>by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Heb. 6.16. <hi>An Oath for confirmation is an end of all ſtrife,</hi> i. e. where there is no end of contradicting, there an Oath is expedient; when the Plaintiff affirms, and the Defendant ſtifly denies, when there is no other way of finding out the Truth, one part of the contradiction being confirmed by the interpoſition of an Oath, the other part ceaſes, and ſo the ſtrife is terminated. Can we imagine then, that the God of peace, unity, and concord, our Lord Chriſt, would wholly forbid <hi>Swearing,</hi> or the uſe of an Oath at any time, or in any caſe, by means whereof, oft-times, as litigious ſuits and ſtrifes at Law are ended, ſo <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> the two moſt firm bonds and liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of humane Society, are preſerved, (for he that lies under a ſolemn Oath, dares not be unfaithful or unjuſt.) I am ſure our Saviour never did forbid it, but only the light, raſh, and vain uſe of an Oath in our ordinary and common diſcourſe; this he did, and ſo our moſt judicious <note n="*" place="margin">Prælect. 7. Sect. 11. ad finem.</note> Biſhop expounds thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34. and the ſame repeated by Saint <hi>James,</hi> Chap. 5.12. which are the <hi>Quakers</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> only <hi>Aſylum,</hi> to which they flie for San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, when they are urged to take an Oath by the Magiſtrate; but I hope they will be effectually beaten, or driven from their <hi>Aſylum,</hi> when their ſhallow and dark underſtandings are better enlightned, and they being convinc'd, ſhall acknowledge in their hearts, though they will hardly confeſs it with their tongues, that the whole weight of their rotten Poſition hangs upon a weak and ſlender thread, even one word, <hi>Omninò, at all,</hi> which is by them miſinterpreted: A good conſtruction whereof is that expreſſion of one <hi>Euſebius</hi> a Gentile Philoſopher in <note n="*" place="margin">Serm. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Stobæus, Many</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97025:15"/>ſayes he there) <hi>exhort men to Swear the Truth; but my exhortation to them is,</hi> Ut ne quidem omnino facilè jurent, <hi>That they Swear not at all eaſily;</hi> he means fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly, without great neceſſity, which is the principal or prime meaning of our Saviours Prohibition, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould here have given a ſtop to my flying Pen, and taken both it and my wearied hand on from this Paper, had not my Zeal inflamed with indignation ſpurred me on to a juſt vindication of the honour of another holy and more ancient <hi>Father,</hi> moſt renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as the former was) in his generation (which was 422. years after Chriſt) for his holy life and ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious knowledge in Divine and Humane Learning, I mean St. <hi>Jerom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 11.</note> whom the <hi>Impoſtor</hi> or <hi>Treatiſt</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges as a Patron of his Opinion, ſaying, (though moſt falſly) <hi>That he makes this the reaſon why God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged the Jews in the uſe of</hi> Swearing, <hi>That they were but in the ſtate of Infancy, and that they might be kept from Swearing by falſe Gods.</hi> I was amazed when I read this, ſo will the judicious Readers be aſtoniſhed at the boldneſs, and madneſs, I may add Falſity and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Treatiſt,</hi> inciting the Gloſs of St. <hi>Jerom</hi> upon that Text, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34. it being ſo clearly and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Father</hi>'s Gloſs is this, which for the benefit of an illiterate <hi>Quaker,</hi> I ſhall tranſlate word for word into Engliſh;<note place="margin">Hanc per ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta juran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di peſſimam conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſemper habuere Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dæi, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>This moſt ungodly cuſtome of Swearing by the Elements was ever in uſe amongst the Jews, for which they are oft condemned by the month of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. He that ſweareth, either worſhippeth or loves him by whom he ſweareth. We are commanded in the Law to Swear by none but by the Lord our God. The Jews ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97025:16"/>by the Angels, by the City of Jeruſalem, by the Temple, and by the Elements, gave that honour and worſhip to the Creatures and carnal things, which was only due to God. But</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Let the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Treatife and his Brethren conſider this.</note> 
               <hi>conſider that our Saviour does not forbid us to Swear by God, but by Heaven, and Earth, by Hieruſalem, and by the Head.</hi> Et hoc, quaſi parvulis fuerat lege con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum: <hi>and this</hi> (ſubaud. <hi>he forbids</hi>) <hi>as if it had been permitted to the Jews, as to little Ones; even as they offer'd Victims unto God, that they might not ſacrifice the ſame unto Idols; ſo they ſhould be permitted to Swear</hi> in Deum <hi>againſt God; not that they ſhould do well in ſo doing, but that it was better to exhibit that honour to God</hi> (viz. <hi>by Swearing by his Temple, &amp;c.</hi>) <hi>than to Dæ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi> From the later part of this Comment begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at, <hi>Et hoc quaſi parvulis, &amp;c.</hi> altogether miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued by him, the <hi>Treatift</hi> (though moſt abſurdly) inferrs that <hi>God indulged</hi> (in the opinion of St <hi>Jerom</hi>) <hi>the Jews in the uſe of Swearing, they being then in the ſtate of Infancy, that they might be kept from Swearing by falſe Gods.</hi> For St. <hi>Jerom</hi> (or to vindicate him) I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to St. <hi>Jerom;</hi> Doth he ſay any ſuch thing? or do his words ſound, or imply any thing to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? I abſolutely deny it. He only ſaith, <q>
                  <hi>That Chriſt forbade his Diſciples to Swear by Heaven and Earth, &amp;c.</hi> Et hoc, <hi>and forbade this,</hi> quaſi, <hi>as if it had been permitted to the Jews in their minority to Swear by them, as it was to offer Victims unto God, that they might not ſacrifice them unto Idols.</hi>
               </q> The Father does not poſitively affirm that God ever permitted the Jews to Swear by any Creature, he ſayes onely <hi>Quaſi, as if it had been permitted.</hi> And let the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> ſhew me any place in the whole Bible, where ever it was tolerated. But this is not the Diſpute now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97025:16"/>
            <p>I muſt only ask him this friendly <hi>Queſtion,</hi> What reaſon he had to paſs by thoſe words of St. <hi>Jerom, Conſider that our Saviour forbids not us to ſwear?</hi> He cannot but anſwer, or I will for him, becauſe it is wholly adverſe to his Poſition: But like as a man that is drowning, catches at any ſmall twig to keep him from ſinking, ſo he to uphold his rotten and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt opinion, layes hold on four words of St. <hi>Jerom, Conceſſum fuerat jurare parvulis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He ſayes not <hi>conceſſum ſuit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>It had been permitted to little Ones for to Swear;</hi> and wilfully omitting what goes before and follows after, concludes from them (which relate only to Swearing by the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) and from <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13, 14. <q>
                  <hi>That God diſpenſed with the Jews for Swearing by his Name, that he might take them off from Swearing by falſe Gods, becauſe thereby they would acknowledge them, and not the true God, ſo that Swearing is only better than Idolatry; Therefore in no caſe good in its own Nature.</hi>
               </q> In anſwer to this, I ſay, that there is a <hi>comparative</hi> without a <hi>poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> as it is better (ſay ſome) to be drunk than to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Fornication, becauſe this is a complicate ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two, the other a ſingle one of one individual perſon. Is it then an evil thing to Swear at all by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocating God's Name? who dares affirm this but an <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> it being an act of Religious Worſhip, as hath been demonſtrated? But I demand again, Did God ever ſay by <hi>Moſes,</hi> or any of his Prophets, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take my Name into thy mouth in any caſe, or at any time?</hi> ſaid he ever this without any reſtriction, or limitation? If he had made this general Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, undoubtedly to take it into our mouths, would be a great and hainous Sin, and ſo the Jews could not have done it lawfully without a ſpecial diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97025:17"/>from God by the mouth of a Prophet: For God being the Supreme Law-giver, whoſe Juriſdiction and Dominion is over all, and above all, may <hi>ad pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citum</hi> diſpenſe with a Negative Precept that forbids a ſin; but then it muſt be either by an inſpired Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, or by a voice from Heaven. Now God never did abſolutely forbid the Jews to Swear by his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Name, but onely <hi>vainly</hi> or <hi>falſly</hi> in the Third Commandment. And this <hi>Negative</hi> includes an <hi>Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative, Thou ſhalt</hi> (when there is an urgent occaſion for it) <hi>Swear by my Name Truly.</hi> He therefore that affirms, that, <hi>God diſpens'd with the Jews for Swearing by his Name,</hi> (which is in its proper nature abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good, becauſe it is allowed of, and enjoyned by God) does in effect ſay, that it is a ſin to invocate, or call upon God, and ſo falls under the Prophet's curſe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Wo unto him that calls good evil, and evil good.</hi> Conſider this thou vain daring man, who doſt plead for a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> to the Jews, which never came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any mans head to think of but thine; neither hadſt thou thought of it, hadſt not thou look't by chance into St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> who by his <hi>Conceſſum ſuerat</hi> never intended any ſuch thing as hath been clearly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced.</p>
            <p>Thou mayſt as well aſſert that God diſpens'd with the Jews to keep the Sabbath day, that they ſhould not celebrate the Feaſts of the Gentiles, as ſay, That he diſpens'd with Swearing by his Name to keep them from Swearing by Idols, or from the Idolatrous Worſhip of the Heathen Gods; the former as well as the later (though both be frivolous) may be averred. And upon this account it would be as great a ſin for Chriſtians to keep the Sabbath, as to ſwear in any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97025:17"/>caſe, if God diſpens'd only with the Jews for either: For, a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> (as it is a comprehenſive term im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying a relaxation of an obligation to any command, ſo that a man may do what the Law prohibits, or not do what it enjoynes) is in the opinion of the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> a conceſſion or grant to do that which is evil in its own nature, and not practicable, or to be done but only by the allowance or approbation of the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, whoſe will is his Law, as being Supreme.</p>
            <p>Now if he can prove by any evidence out of the Goſpel or Evangeliſts, that to Swear is a ſin in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per nature (with which the Jews, as he falſly aſſerts, were diſpens'd by God) if he can do this (which I know is impoſſible) I will recant what I have writ, and exhort all my Friends and good Chriſtians not to Swear at all.</p>
            <p>I am confident that the Author of the Treatiſe was ſtartled, and put to a ſtaining bluſh when he peruſed St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Gloſs upon our Saviour's words, and met with his <note n="*" place="margin">Conſidera quod hic Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator per De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um jurare non prohibuerit.</note> 
               <hi>Conſidera</hi> in the middle of it, <q>
                  <hi>Conſider that our Saviour here forbade not Swearing by the Name of God,</hi>
               </q> but only vain, raſh, and impertinent Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſurely he conſider'd it, but being diſpleas'd with the Holy Man for his opinion, and angry at his Exhortation, ſtudied a revenge, which was to blaſt him with a Lye, and make him guilty of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, by ſaying in effect, that what he appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of, was a ſin, yet not diſprov'd of in the Jews by means of God's ſpecial <hi>Diſpenſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all that has been ſaid in Vindication of Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> and the forenamed Father, may be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concluded, That the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> has been bred up in the Jeſuits School, in which is taught that Diabolical
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97025:18"/>Arithmetical Art of <hi>Subtraction, Addition</hi> and <hi>Diviſion,</hi> to which may be added that black Art of <hi>Detraction,</hi> for that he to the Biſhops Book <hi>De Juramenti Oblig.</hi> has <hi>added</hi> what he never writ; to St. <hi>Jerom</hi> he has <hi>ſubtracted</hi> (by <hi>dividing</hi> the former part of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the later) what the Father has plainly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and is a refutation of what he endeavours to maintain, which is a great Falſity, and repugnant to Scripture Truth; and in all, he has by a foul and dirty Pen <hi>detracted</hi> from both their reputations and credit.</p>
            <p>Thus too he hath done by the Reverend Doctor <hi>Gawden</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and before that of <hi>Exeter,</hi> whom he hath peremptorily liſted amongſt thoſe who ſeem to favour his Opinion (as being an <hi>Antijuriſt</hi>) and laid (as I may ſay) this <hi>Baſtard</hi> at his door, begot by the Father of Lyes, upon an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> darkned with Errour, and brought forth by the <hi>Midwifry</hi> of an unruly malepert <hi>Tongue,</hi> and nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up by the help of a virulent <hi>Pen.</hi> But what hath that holy Biſhop, that righteous man (whom none can read but with amazement or admiration, both for the floridneſs of his <hi>Style,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>-like <hi>Tongue,</hi> together with his profundity of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and great variety of <hi>Learning,</hi> as is evident by his Printed Works, eſpecially his <hi>Eccleſiæ Anglicanæ Suſpiria</hi>) what hath he done or ſaid, that they ſhould chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, or own him for their <hi>Patron?</hi> I'le tell you firſt what he hath ſaid of <hi>Them,</hi> and then what they quote out of <hi>Him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Oaths. Pag. 4.</note> Firſt he ſays of <hi>Them,</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>That they have a canting or Chymical Divinity, which bubbles forth many ſpecious</hi> Notions, <hi>fine fancies, &amp; ſhort-liv'd Conceptions, floating a little in an airy and empty brain, but not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during the firm touch or breath of any ſerious Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </q>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97025:18"/>And Pag. 7. <q>
                  <hi>I profeſs there appears to me ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of an excellent or Extraordinary Spirit in them, that there is much of</hi> Sillineſs, <hi>and not well-catechis'd</hi> Ignorance, <hi>ſet off with a great Confidence.</hi>
               </q> Again, <q>
                  <hi>They generally ſeem a buſie, petulant, and pragmatick ſort of people, meaſuring</hi> themſelves <hi>by</hi> themſelves,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.12.</note> 
                  <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring each other, even in their ridiculous</hi> Affectations, <hi>and</hi> Falſities; <hi>a kind of</hi> Dreamers,<note place="margin">Iud. 8. 2 Pet. 3.13.</note> 
                  <hi>at once</hi> deceiving and being deceived, <hi>doting and glorying in their rude and contemptuous carriage towards all men, that do not either favour, or flatter them in their ruſticity and petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy, which hath in it a great ſeed of Pride and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition.</hi>
               </q> And in his Suſpir. Anglic. pag. 73. He terms them, <q>
                  <hi>The meaneſt and ſhort-ſpirited men, who in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious differences, and in the matter of</hi> Ceremonies, <hi>do affect to appear moſt cruelly Zealous, and unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably pertinacious.</hi>
               </q> This is the <hi>Character</hi> he gives of them. But what ſayes the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> of him?</p>
            <p>Nothing, I confeſs, derogatory to his perſon, but he quotes, or cites only a remarkable ſaying of his, which makes much againſt the <hi>Anti-Juriſts,</hi> it is this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 154.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>The evil of mens hearts and manners, the jealouſies and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſts, the diſſimulations and frauds of many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, their uncharitableneſs, unſatisfactions, and inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities, are ſuch, and ſo great Diſeaſes, as make the application of</hi> Solemn Oaths <hi>and</hi> Judicial Swearing <hi>neceſſary by way of</hi> Conſequence <hi>and</hi> Remedy.</q> What replyes the <hi>Quaker</hi> to this? His anſwer is, That there is no need of theſe applications to him or his Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and why? <hi>Becauſe, forſooth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 155</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt who is the Reſtorer of Breaches, and builder of Waſte-places, has redeemed them into Truth-ſpeaking, which takes away the Occaſion of an Oath, and ſuch as are the true, humble,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97025:19"/>and faithful followers of this</hi> Worthy, <hi>need no Oath to compel them into Truth, to whom it's natural</hi> (My good Friend, I thought it had been a work of Gods Grace) <hi>being freed by it from fraud and falſeneſs, and conſequently from</hi> Swearing, <hi>which took occaſion by it to enter into the World.</hi> To all which he ſubjoyns this ſolemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation in the name of his <hi>Friends</hi> (as he calls them) <hi>i. e.</hi> his fellow-<hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
               <hi>Now we profeſs our ſelves in the fear of Almighty God to be ſuch, as have thus learned Jeſus Chriſt, and for the Reverence, and holy Love we bear to his righteous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, we cannot take an Oath in any caſe.</hi> In anſwer to this <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> I muſt, <hi>Firſt,</hi> tell the <hi>Profeſſour,</hi> that there is no ſuch command of Chriſt, he never forbade us to Swear in any caſe; this hath been ſufficiently il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated and proved. <hi>Secondly,</hi> he muſt give me leave to be his <hi>Inſtructor</hi> and <hi>Teacher,</hi> and make him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that his former <hi>Profeſſion</hi> is a <hi>Formal Oath,</hi> as having the Form or Eſſence of an <hi>Oath</hi> in it, which conſiſts in a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of God and his Almighty Power, as this implies an <hi>Invocation</hi> of God to be a <hi>Witneſs</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> of what we ſpeak or affirm; and I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that it is an Untruth what is affirmed by him, <hi>viz. That Chriſt taught us, Not to Swear in any caſe.</hi> So then, the <hi>tantamount</hi> or ſum of their <hi>Profeſſion</hi> is this, <hi>In the preſence of God, whom we confeſs and acknowledge to be</hi> Almighty <hi>and accordingly fear him, becauſe he is able, and will deſtroy us if we profeſs a Lye</hi>— What is this but a <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Swearing,</hi> even as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, when he made a Profeſſion of his Sincerity, ſaying, <hi>Before God I Lye not?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 1.20.</note> So the Quaker by an implicite calling upon God to be a Witneſs of what he ſayes, <hi>viz. That he has learned of Chriſt not to Swear at all,</hi> does
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97025:19"/>indeed <hi>Swear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thus a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer being once rebuked for his Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Swore that he would Swear no more. Tit. 3.2.</note> and that too which is falſe (for he has not been ſo taught of Chriſt) therefore he calls God to witneſs an Untruth; and what is this but <hi>falſe Swearing,</hi> which another would cloath with an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (though proper) term? But as I deſire to be <hi>gentle ſhewing all meekneſs to all men,</hi> (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts) ſo <hi>parcè loquor,</hi> I forbear to name it, as fearing that I ſhould, by mentioning that, at which my heart trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, put the poor miſtaken man into a new fit of <hi>Quaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He <hi>proteſted</hi> that he could not <hi>Swear,</hi> and did it in <hi>protesting:</hi> It ſeems the man of great Reading and pretended Knowledge, was ignorant of the <hi>material</hi> parts of a <hi>Formal Oath;</hi> ſo was not another grand <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of <hi>Quakeriſme</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> one <hi>E. C.</hi> who is yet living; ſparing his Name, I ſhall faithfully relate what was lately reported to me of him a profeſſed <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer,</hi> and <hi>Factour</hi> for ſome <hi>Merchants</hi> here in <hi>London.</hi> The ſtory of him is this; There was a <hi>Bill</hi> not long ſince put into the <hi>Chancery</hi> there againſt him, in a Money buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to which he was commanded to give in his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> upon <hi>Oath,</hi> the which he refuſed, and after ſome delayes addreſſed himſelf to a worthy perſon Dr. <hi>W.</hi> one of the Maſters of the foreſaid Court, proffering him Twenty Pieces in Gold if he would exempt him from <hi>Swearing,</hi> and admit of his <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay</hi> to his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,</hi> and all <hi>Interrogatories</hi> that ſhould be propoſed unto him; the Doctor, as it became him, ſent him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a ſharp reprehenſion for his boldneſs, and wicked attempt to corrupt him. Upon this he was more bold in petitioning the <hi>Lord Deputy</hi> that his <hi>Yea, &amp;c.</hi> might be admitted, but was likewiſe with a ſevere check diſmiſſed unſatisfied; at laſt, when he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97025:20"/>perceived,<note place="margin">To this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſome of his party may reply, that he was forced Swear againſt his mind up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neceſſity, but we ſay, that no honeſt man will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience Swear a falſity.</note> that unleſs he made <hi>Oath</hi> to his <hi>Anſwer</hi> he ſhould be non-ſuited, he diſpens'd with his tender Conſcience, and took it; after which, there came in ſuch ſtrong evidences againſt him, that he was found guilty of <hi>Perjury,</hi> and caſt in the Suit between him and the <hi>Plaintiff.</hi> By this may be collected what cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit is to be given to a <hi>Quaker</hi>'s <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> when as, if the man has a falſe heart, under the covert of it a <hi>Lye</hi> may be ſhelter'd.</p>
            <p>But leaving him to Chriſtian Pity, and God's mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, I muſt return from this ſhort digreſſion, and from the former falſe <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> reflect upon his vain <hi>Oſtentation,</hi> apparent in his <hi>Protestation</hi> (which goes before it, <hi>Pag.</hi> 155. of the Treatiſe) <hi>viz. That Christ has redeemed him and the rest of his Combination into Truth-ſpeaking, which takes away the Occaſion of an Oath.</hi> What is this but <hi>Phariſaiſme,</hi> or proud boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becoming a <hi>Thraſo</hi> or <hi>Miles glorioſus</hi> in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, rather than the mouth of a Chriſtian, being one of the many marks which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> fixes upon an unregenerate and carnal man,<note place="margin">Deſpightful, proud, Boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. Moreover he ſaith, (and what is it but perfect <hi>Pelagianiſm?</hi>) that <hi>Truth is natural unto them;</hi> if it be the fruit of <hi>Nature,</hi> then it is not of <hi>Grace:</hi> what could have been ſaid more by <hi>Pelagius,</hi> or his Diſciple <hi>Faustus!</hi> Omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a farther Refutation of his vain-glorious and proud. <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> I ſhall plainly diſcover unto him the falſity of it by this one direct Syllogiſme, <hi>They that are redeemed by Christ into Truth-ſpeaking, to whom Truth is natural, need no Oath to compel them to Truth; but, we the true, humble, and faithful followers of Christ are ſuch;</hi> Ergo, <hi>we need not an Oath.</hi> I could deny the <hi>Major Propoſition,</hi> as being falſe (as I ſhall prove here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after;)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97025:20"/>but for the preſent I deny the <hi>Aſſumption</hi> or <hi>Minor;</hi> and to manifeſt the truth of my denial, I ſhall not make uſe (as I might) of a <hi>Sorites</hi> by an enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration of particular perſons among them, and from them whoſe Lives and Actions have witneſſed the contrary, draw a <hi>Negative</hi> Concluſion, I will onely ask the man of <hi>Truth,</hi> I mean the <hi>Profeſſing Treatiſt,</hi> this one Queſtion, If Truth-ſpeaking, or Veracity be natural to him, and all things by Nature ever the ſame, without any the leaſt change or alteration (as the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher</hi> atteſts) why then contrary to his <hi>Nature</hi> which muſt argue a perverſeneſs in his Will) and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Rules or common moral Honeſty (which argues a pravity in his <hi>Nature</hi>) did he belye two emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Fathers</hi> or the Church by endeavouring to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the world that they ſaid or writ what they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt.</note> And if Chriſt's Saints be <hi>redeemed</hi> by him into <hi>Truth-ſpeaking,</hi> then they that make no conſcience of a Lye, or <hi>that love, and make a Lye,</hi> are neither Saints nor redeemed by Chriſt; I am ſure Saint <hi>John</hi> reckons them amongſt thoſe that ſhall never enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven (ſuch are <hi>Sorcerers, Whoremongers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 22.15.</note> 
               <hi>Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Idolaters</hi>) without an high degree or meaſure of repentance.</p>
            <p>Once more, If he be a man of <hi>Truth,</hi> why <hi>walks</hi> not he then <hi>in the Truth,</hi> or as the <hi>Rule</hi> of Truth, the Word of God, directeth?<note place="margin">2 Ep. Ioh. 4.</note> This commands us to <hi>give honour to whom honour is due,</hi> Rom. 13.7. and to <hi>honour the King,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.17. This neither he, nor any of his rude Tribe will do, witneſs his, and his <hi>Aſſociates</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerlineſs, and proud demeanour even towards the <hi>King,</hi> and great perſons of <hi>Honour,</hi> to whom they meaſure the ſame <hi>Omer</hi> of reſpect which they do to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97025:21"/>their Equals, and Inferiours, witneſs their <hi>Thouing</hi> and <hi>Theeing</hi> them, and covered heads before them, which betokens no Humility, but much Pride to be in their hearts, proceeding from a pretence, or phanſie that there is a Diviner <hi>Spirit,</hi> and a brighter <hi>Light</hi> in them, than either <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Scripture,</hi> or great <hi>Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> affords to others, whereby they think that they have cauſe to glory in their illuminations, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe all thoſe who have not arrived to the pitch or height of their preſumptuous Phanſies. But that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly rudeneſs might be born with, if they would give the <hi>Lord</hi> of Heaven the honour that is due unto him,<note place="margin">Hebr. 13 17. Obey them that &amp;c.</note> by obeying his commands, in obeying the <hi>King</hi>'s Laws tending to <hi>Decency, Order,</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> both in State and Church: And becauſe they are reſolved to live and dye in a conſtant oppoſition to all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they therefore will take no Oath which may bind them to ſubmit unto it; nay, they will not take an Oath when it is offered by the Magiſtrate, when they might thereby determine a Controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and man, put an end or give a ſtop to a vexatious Suit in Law, or promote their Neighbours welfare, by giving thereby a firm Teſtimony of his ſuſpected Honeſty: and does not this argue a great want of <hi>Charity?</hi> Nay, a <hi>Quaker</hi> will not Swear though he might thereby ſave his Neighbour's life: and is not this an high piece of <hi>Cruelty?</hi> So obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unmerciful, ſo ſtiffly uncharitable is this <hi>Quaking</hi> Tribe, that as they ought to do no evil that good may come of it; ſo they will not do that which is in it ſelf good (ſuch is the taking of a <hi>Lawful Oath</hi>) to prevent a great evil, damage, or hurt that may or will befall a Neighbour, be it the loſing of an Eſtate.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97025:21"/>Are ſuch men governed and guided by the good Spirit of Chriſt? I cannot omit here to relate a Story of a <hi>Quakers</hi> obſtinacy, who could not be invited to <hi>Swear</hi> the Truth of that whereof he was an eye witneſs, it is this. <note n="*" place="margin">I was my ſelf an Ear witneſs of this private Buſineſs.</note> A <hi>Mariner</hi> going to Sea, and being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for a long Voyage, gave a Bill of Attorney to his Wife, enabling her to receive his Wages in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; now becauſe (as it is ordered by the <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners</hi> for the Navie) no ſuch moneys will be paid unleſs the Bill be atteſted by a Witneſs Sworn before a <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> that he was preſent at the writing of it, it happened that a Neighbour poyſoned with the <hi>Quaker</hi>'s Principles (being one of their Diſciples) was only preſent when the <hi>Seaman</hi> writ it, and being deſir'd by his Wife to witneſs the ſame, he refus'd to appear before the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and could not be perſwaded to take the Oath which was to be miniſtred unto him, by which means the poor woman would be deprived of her maintenance, if her husband had been gone to Sea, and not Tranſcribed the foreſaid Bill in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of an honeſt Man, who thought it no ſin to ſwear for the benefit of another, being aſſured that it was not (as it is not) repugnant to any command of our <hi>Saviour.</hi> Now it is eaſie to determine which of theſe two is the better <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> there is no wiſe man but will give his ſentence for the latter, and not think him worthy of the name of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> who wants that which is the life and ſoul of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and that is (with <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Humility</hi>) an Univerſal <hi>Charity</hi> to all men, which is a <hi>diffuſive</hi> Grace prompting a man to be beneficial even to his enemies, and not contract his love and kindneſs only to thoſe who are of his party, and combine with him in his opinions, though they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97025:22"/>be repugnant to the truth in the holy Scriptures. Such is the narrow, and ſhort-breath'd <hi>Charity</hi> of the <hi>Anti-Juriſts,</hi> whoſe <hi>Opinion</hi> (or falſe conceit) of the <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſinfulneſs</hi> of all <hi>Judicial</hi> and <hi>State</hi> Oaths, is both <hi>unchriſtian,</hi> as being <hi>uncharitable,</hi> in that as it hinders them from doing good to their Friends and Neighbours, ſo if it were embrac'd by all (as it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will) it would <hi>impede</hi> in Courts of Judicature the due adminiſtration of Juſtice; it is likewiſe <hi>deſtructive</hi> and very dangerous, in regard that the <hi>Safety, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Tranquillity</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> cannot without Oaths (I mean thoſe of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi>) be ſecured againſt the Traiterous plottings, and miſchievous deſigns of domeſtick and inteſtine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> and others, <hi>Antipapists</hi> in the points of ſome fundamental Doctrines, but <hi>Co-papiſts,</hi> as being Adverſaries of the Churches Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>The contrary opinion of the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> and <hi>unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the forenamed <hi>Publick</hi> Oaths, is agreeable to the word of God, ratified by the continued <hi>Customes</hi> of this and all other Nations, both <hi>Eccleſiaſtical, Civil,</hi> or <hi>Common;</hi> and approved of by the beſt of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in all ages, by the conſonant unanimous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> and modern <hi>Writers</hi> of the <hi>Reformed</hi> Churches, (together with the moſt eminent <hi>Divines</hi> in ours,) it is alſo confirmed by the <hi>Harmony</hi> of their <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> both <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinists,</hi> by all <hi>Canonists,</hi> and <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> all of them in a juſt ſeverity condemning the uſe of <hi>Falſe, idle,</hi> and profane Oaths, aſſert the Authority of lawful Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates (which the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> and his <hi>Abettors</hi> proudly deny) to require and impoſe religious Oaths, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that it is the duty of Subjects to take them, as it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97025:22"/>becomes Chriſtians, with due reverence to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> of God, and fitting obedience to the commands of <hi>Superiour</hi> and <hi>Inferiour Magiſtrates,</hi> who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with their power from God, and are to uſe it to his glory and the welfare of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-Wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This bright <hi>Cloud</hi> of Witneſſes to the Truth I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay that I oppoſe to the 200 and 7. Authorities muſtered up in a Catalogue plac'd in the front of the <hi>Quaker's Treatiſe,</hi> for, <note n="*" place="margin">As Chryſoſt. Auguſtine, Ierome, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius, &amp;c.</note> moſt of them onely inveigh without any limitation, or reſerve againſt mens eaſie &amp; ordinary courſe of <hi>Swearing</hi> in private converſation, yet holding it lawful both to give and take an <hi>Oath</hi> in great and weighty concerns for a ratification of Truth, and eſtabliſhing of Juſtice. As for ſome others of them cited in his <hi>Catalogue,</hi> they were tainted with the Hereſies of the <hi>Samoſatenians, Pelagians, Maſſilians,</hi> and the <hi>Euchites,</hi> and of their diſciples or followers in their opinion againſt <hi>Swearing at all,</hi> the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> to whom we may add the <hi>Meniſts</hi> in the <hi>Netherlands</hi> mentioned by the <hi>Treatiſt,</hi> p. 157. for this reaſon they are not to be held for competent Judges in the caſe, neither are their authorities to be admitted; ſo are the Arguments drawn from the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and practiſes of a few godly Martyrs to be rejected, to wit, of <hi>Baſilides</hi> and <hi>Polycarpus</hi> who only refuſed Oaths propounded to them which were in the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>form</hi> of them ſinful, as to ſwear by the <hi>Fortune</hi> of <hi>Cæſar,</hi> which <hi>Polycarpus</hi> denied, or by the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Emperor, which <hi>Baſilides</hi> and <hi>Speratus</hi> refuſed,<note place="margin">Pondere rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis haud Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorum nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero eſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuranda veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</note> as is to be ſeen in <hi>Euſebius.</hi> I do therefore conclude, and repeat what I premiſed in my <hi>Preface</hi> that the <hi>Treatiſt's</hi> 207 <hi>Authorities</hi> are to little or no purpoſe, rather
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97025:23"/>againſt, than for him, and his <hi>Co-Anti-Juriſts.</hi> Nay; I add and ſay, put caſe he had produc'd a thouſand move <hi>Authorities</hi> againſt all kind of Swearing,<note place="margin">Tert. li. Præſcrip. cont. Hær <hi>To this ſaying</hi> Tert. <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t me add thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of</hi> S. Ambroſe, Nolo nobis credatur, recitetur Scriptura.</note> I would retort to them all with that ſaying of <hi>Tertullian. Non experſonis fidem, ſed ex fide perſonas metiamur, we muſt not meaſure the Truth by the perſons of Men,</hi> as to ſay it is true <hi>becauſe</hi> ſuch a Learned man ſaid it, but in ſo <hi>becauſe</hi> the <hi>Word of God</hi> does maintain it; and thoſe perſons (though never ſo holy in outward appearance) are not to be commended, or imitated, who out of a ſcrupulous, nice, erroneous conſcience ſhall refuſe to do that which the ſame <hi>word</hi> alloweth, ſo is <hi>Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Swearing.</hi> Therefore the poor deceived <hi>Quakers</hi> (whoſe ignorance I pitty) are in a dangerous error, being <hi>Affirmatively ſuperſtitious,</hi> in counting that a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is not, and <hi>Negatively,</hi> in abſtaining from that as ſin, which is no ſin, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> from all kind <hi>of Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 53.5.</note>As preſumptuous confidences where there is no Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine permiſſion, ſo erroneous <hi>fears where no fear</hi> ought to be, are very dangerous, and caſt a ſnare upon the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>I have one thing more (and that material) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the <hi>Treatiſt,</hi> that is, whether he was <hi>compos mentis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 3.</note> and not tranſported by a whim of Phanſie, when he was bold to make a <hi>Propoſal</hi> in the Preface of his <hi>Pamphlet</hi> dedicated to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> that the <hi>Quakers Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay</hi> (which is the mark in their mouths whereby they are known and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from others) may ſtand for an <hi>Oath, they being willing if they ſhould ever be convinced of a Lye</hi> (by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing what they performed not, or aſſerting an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth) <hi>to ſuſtain the ſame Penalty that is uſually inflicted
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97025:23"/>on Perjury.</hi> What was all this but to deſire that the <hi>old</hi> Forms of <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Judicial</hi> Oaths ſhould be alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and turned into <hi>New?</hi> I'le inſtance onely in the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> (which involves in the body of it that other of <hi>Supremacy</hi>) in the propounding of which to <hi>W. P.</hi> or to any or his <hi>Brethren,</hi> the Magiſtrate muſt (if the others requeſt be granted) act the part of a <hi>Catechiſt,</hi> in theſe terms: <q>
                  <hi>Doſt thou</hi> W. P. <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the</hi> Kings Highneſs <hi>to be the onely Supream</hi> Governour <hi>of this Realm, and of all other His</hi> High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes <hi>Dominions, and Countreys, in all Cauſes and over all perſons whether</hi> Eccleſiaſtical <hi>or</hi> Civil, <hi>and do you promiſe that you will bear faith, and true Allegiance to his Majeſty, and defend Him to the utmoſt of your power againſt all conſpiracies, and attempts whatſoever againſt his Crown and Dignity, and do your beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to declare, and make known to his Majeſty his Heirs and Succeſſors all Treaſons and Traiterous Conſpiracies which you ſhall know or hear to be made againſt him?</hi>
               </q> To all theſe interrogations the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed honeſt <hi>W. P.</hi> will ſay <hi>Yea,</hi> and if I break my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe let the Penalty of <hi>Perjury</hi> be inflicted on me. I pray what is all this but <hi>Canting?</hi> cunningneſs, and craft lies at the bottom of it: What is the puniſhment of a <hi>Perjured</hi> perſon? It is to loſe his cars in a Pillory, and not to be admitted for a witneſs in any <hi>Court of Juſtice,</hi> &amp;c. Now conſider how favourable a motion the good man has made for himſelf and his Brethren! He cannot but know, and be aſſured of it, that if he breaks his promiſe, by joyning in a private Conſpiracy againſt the <hi>King,</hi> or by open rebellion raiſing any popular commotion, or tumults, he will be indicted for <hi>Felony</hi> or <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and ſo loſe his life in an halter inſtead of his ears.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:97025:24"/>
            <p>And what ſecuritie can the <hi>King</hi> have from <hi>W. P.</hi> (or any of his <hi>Tribe</hi>) for his own ſafety and the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> Peace, or be aſſured that he will keep his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and not be attached for a <hi>Lye</hi> in breaking of it, when he (the ſuppoſed prime <hi>Penman</hi> of the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe</hi>) makes no conſcience to aſſert or affirm what is moſt falſe, as in the Caſe of Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> and Saint <hi>Jerom,</hi> hath been demonſtrated to his great ſhame. He that ſhall once baffle me with a bold lye, I will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take his word, or reſt in his <hi>Yea;</hi> and he that has <hi>invented,</hi> and publickly <hi>vented</hi> one out of the Preſs, it may be ſuſpected he will not keep his private promiſe, and that his bare word will not bind him to an exact performance, which a ſolemn <hi>Oath</hi> might do, whereby he calls God to be both a <hi>witneſs</hi> of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,<note place="margin">Num. 22.31.</note> and a ſevere Judge to puniſh him both in body and ſoul if he be a <hi>Promiſſifragus.</hi> An <hi>Oath</hi> like to the <hi>Angel</hi> with a glittering Sword in his hand, who ſtopped <hi>Balaam</hi> in his way to <hi>Balak,</hi> is of more force, and energy than a naked word to bind a man to his duty; and there is no man that has an honeſt heart and meaning, and knows the many temptations he is expoſed to from his own corrupt nature, the <hi>Fleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> but will chearifully, and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take an Oath firſt praying to God that he may have, by his grace, ſtrength and power to keep it) whereby he may be the more aw'd by fear of God's vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Juſtice, to be faithful and juſt in the diſcharge of his duty, or any publick office, which will procure to him the peace of a quiet mind or indiſtur'd <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> which is a great bleſſing, and is gain'd many times by means of a <hi>Promiſſory</hi> Oath in <hi>Swearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is beſides the former <hi>Propoſal</hi> of the <hi>Quakers,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:97025:24"/>a <hi>Queſtion</hi> put by the Author of the <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> whom I find to be in divers ſhapes, ſometimes acting the part of a <hi>Pelagian</hi> in ſaying, that <hi>Truth</hi> (which is a grace of God) is natural to him, next of a perfect <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> as in the point of <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> to the Jews, and his falſe Citati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and corrupting of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and now the part of a downright audacious <hi>Quaker,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 14.15</note> 
               <hi>Quo te Conſtringam vultus mutantem Protea nodo?</hi> His <hi>Quære</hi> is this, <hi>Why</hi> their <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay</hi> may not be admitted inſtead of an <hi>Oath,</hi> as well as the <hi>Lords</hi> Avouchment upon their <hi>Honour?</hi> by which muſt be underſtood <hi>Vertue</hi> in the ſenſe of the beſt and moſt ancient <hi>Philoſophers:</hi> what does he infer from this, (though he be miſtaken in the proper notion of <hi>Vertue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">His words are, Vertue needs not Swear &amp;c.</note> and belyes too the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers?</hi>) This is his Inference (or to this effect) <hi>We are</hi> Vertuous perſons, therefore <hi>we need not Swear, much leſs have Oaths impos'd upon us to tell the Truth,</hi> the <hi>onely uſe of Oaths.</hi> My good vertuous Friend, I muſt tell thee mildly, this is a Thraſonical brag. But to come to the <hi>Quære,</hi> My anſwer to it in general is, That it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, and incongruous, For <hi>firſt</hi> the <hi>Quaker's Yea</hi> is onely a ſimple Affirmation to aſſert the <hi>Truth,</hi> or what has been ſaid or done, a Queſtion to this purpoſe having been put unto him; But the <hi>Avouchment</hi> of a Lord upon his Honour, is a more ſolemn Proteſtation and <hi>Aſſeveration</hi> of a Truth, and implies an <hi>Option,</hi> or wiſh, (as an Oath does an <hi>Imprecation</hi>) and the ſenſe or meaning of it (being but an abridgment of his <note n="*" place="margin">This Form was antiently the Lords Proteſtation.</note> 
               <hi>per Fidem &amp; Allegiantiam meam</hi>) is this, <q>
                  <hi>As I bear true Faith and Allegiance to my Soveraign Lord the King, ſo is that which I ſay moſt</hi> true, and if I witneſs an untruth, or promiſe what I do not purpoſe, nor will perform; let diſgrace and reproach fall upon my Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97025:25"/>perſon, let me liſted amongſt thoſe that are diſloyal and not faithful to their King, let me be counted for a vile perſon unworthy of any honour, or reſpect from men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> So that by <hi>Honour</hi> is not meant <hi>Vertue</hi> properly ſo called, as the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> fondly imagines, for <hi>Vertue</hi> (or vertuous actions) is onely the ground of Honour, which is, <hi>In honorante</hi> not <hi>in honorato</hi> (as the <note n="*" place="margin">Ariſtot.</note> Philoſopher atteſts in his <hi>Ethicks,</hi> or Book of <hi>Manners,</hi> which the <hi>Quaker</hi> never ſtudied) <hi>It is in</hi> the <hi>Honourer,</hi> not <hi>in him that is honoured,</hi> being nothing elſe but an high <hi>eſteem</hi> and outward Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which men have of, and exhibit to a <hi>Noble</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for his Vertue, for his Piety towards <hi>God,</hi> and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to his <hi>King.</hi> By this we may collect how the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> is miſtaken, I will not ſay for want of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to which he pretends by citing many <hi>Authors,</hi> (and it argues a cripple or lame Cauſe that needs ſo many Crutches) I rather impute it to his Sophiſtical crafty induſtrie, in laying hold on any thing, though it be but one word, by which, and that miſunderſtood, he may gain a little countenance to his exploded Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>Beſides this he cannot be excuſed for his Malapert rudeneſs, who dares put himſelf into the <hi>Scales</hi> with the beſt of the Lords (and thoſe vertuous Perſons) and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that becauſe in ſome caſes they have a priviledge to atteſt onely <hi>upon their Honours,</hi> therefore he may challenge the ſame for his <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> by which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny credulous and well-meaning men have been delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and drawn into Errours; witneſs <hi>E. B.</hi> a late Brewer in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who is famous, <hi>rather infamous, for cheating all his</hi> Creditors <hi>to the ruine of many</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:97025:25"/>
            <p>Moreover I muſt acquaint him, for a further refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his bold <hi>Propoſal,</hi> with what I have learn'd from that great <hi>Oracle</hi> of Law, and Law-Caſes, Sir <hi>Ed. Cook</hi> in the 12 Part of his <hi>Reports,</hi> p. 95, 96. There he tells us, that <q>
                  <hi>If any one who is</hi> Noble, <hi>and a</hi> Peer <hi>of the Realm be ſued in</hi> Chancery, <hi>he ought to anſwer upon his</hi> Oath; <hi>and, if any Noble perſon be produced as a witneſs between party and party, he ought to be ſworn, or otherwiſe his Testimony is of no value; in theſe caſes his atteſtation, or</hi> Avouchment upon his Honour <hi>will not be admitted, though in many others it may and ought to be accepted.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, I muſt in lieu of his <hi>Propoſal</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> propound a Queſtion to him, which is, whether the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Lords</hi> both <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> committed an hainous ſin, when his <hi>Majeſty at his Coronation,</hi> bound himſelf (by a gracious condeſcenſion) in an <hi>Oath</hi> to diſcharge faithfully that great Truſt for the wellfare of the Church and State committed by God unto him, and they likewiſe obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves by a reciprocal <hi>Oath</hi> to be <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Faithful</hi> to him, with this cloſe, <hi>So help me God,</hi> hereby invocating God to be a <hi>Witneſs</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> of what they had ſworn, and deſiring no help or mercy from him, if they ſhould ever rebell againſt their <hi>King?</hi> Dares the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> or his <hi>Fellow-Quakers</hi> ſay that they ſinned or broke Chriſt's command by doing it? I preſume they dare not, nay they cannot, without being guilty of a lye; and to ſay that it is a ſin to invocate or call upon God, is no leſs than blaſphemy. From hence I infer, that their general <hi>Theſis,</hi> to wit, <hi>That it is not lawful to Swear in any caſe,</hi> is abſurd, falſe, and ridiculous.</p>
            <p>So it is likewiſe of a dangerous <hi>Conſequence,</hi> as tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſubverſion of Order, the deſtruction of good
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97025:26"/>Manners (which they want) in <hi>States, Polities,</hi> and <hi>Common-wealths,</hi> together with the ſtopping of legal proceedings in <hi>Courts of Judicature</hi> (as hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) and before <hi>Juſtices of the Peace.</hi> In the foreſaid publick Courts of Juſtice, there is a moſt neceſſary uſe of an <hi>Aſſertory</hi> Oath to find out the Truth as to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular facts or actions; of a <hi>Promiſſory</hi> Oath there is not ſo much need, or uſe in them: This is neceſſary in <hi>Publick,</hi> and <hi>Private</hi> matters, which are called by the Lawyers <hi>Extrajudicial,</hi> the uſe of it in theſe is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Subjects in their <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Fidelity</hi> to their <hi>King,</hi> for this end were framed the Oaths of <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> the firſt in the beginning of the Raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the laſt in the third of King <hi>James.</hi> It is likewiſe morally neceſſary to confirm Leagues and Covenants contracted between <hi>Princes</hi> &amp; <hi>Common-wealths,</hi> To the keeping of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> and conſequently the honour, order, and peace of <hi>Colledges,</hi> and <hi>Societies;</hi> To the binding of all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Officers to an honeſt and faithful diſcharge of their duties, To ratifie private bargains between Buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Sellers, when it is required by any one of them, who ſuſpects the others Truth and Honeſty in his deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but in this latter caſe, I could <hi>wiſh,</hi> that <hi>Oaths</hi> might be forborn, and rather other means uſed, with leſs hazzard to Conſcience, ſuch are <hi>Pawns,</hi> and <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, Bonds,</hi> and <hi>Handwritings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the former <hi>Wiſh,</hi> I ſhall add another; That all profane and blaſpheming <hi>Rabſheka's</hi> would in this one thing imitate the (ſo called) <hi>Quakers,</hi> (and for which they cannot but be commended) who have ſo great a fear of an <hi>Oath</hi> as they pretend) that out of a timorous jealouſie of Swearing amiſs they will <hi>not Swear at all,</hi> by them the other may learn to have a juſt abhorrence
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97025:26"/>of the ſin of eaſie, trivial, familiar, inconſiderate, and vain <hi>Swearing,</hi> which brings a curſe upon a man,<note place="margin">Iurandi facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium labimur. Aug.</note> and his family, and diſpoſeth men to that horrid Sin, a ſin of the firſt magnitude, that is <hi>Perjury,</hi> or <hi>falſe Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> of which a <hi>Lye</hi> (moſt abominable to God) is the Ingredient, beſides the affront, irreverence, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour done to God, by calling upon him to witneſs an <hi>untruth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have a third <hi>Option,</hi> it is my hearty with and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> and his Confederates would enter their names in the School of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccieſ. 7.16.</note> and learn of <hi>Solomon</hi> this wholeſom leſſon of <hi>moderation, Be not righteous overmuch, neither make thy ſelf overwiſe, why ſhouldſt thou destroy thy ſelf?</hi> This Precept is of a great extent and latitude,<note place="margin">Mercerus.</note> but the learned <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of the <hi>Hebrew Tongue</hi> in <hi>Paris</hi> impales, and confines it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſs of theſe three Words, <hi>Ne ſis juſtus ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium, Be not over-righteous,</hi> (i.e.) Be not <hi>Severe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leges mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randas docet nec ſeverius exigendas. . ibid.</note> be not <hi>Superſtitious,</hi> be not <hi>Perverſe.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Be not Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere,</hi> ſo it concerns the <hi>Judge,</hi> exhorting him by a mild interpretation to mitigate the rigour or the Laws, and not tourge and preſs the bare letter of them againſt Offenders, that break them either out of weakneſs, or ignorance. Secondly, Be not <hi>Superſtitious,</hi> ſo it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the <hi>Romanists,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuſti nimium ſunt <hi>(i.e)</hi> videri volunt, qui in ſuis operibus Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem collocant Idem.</note> and condemns their works of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererrogation,</hi> their going on <hi>Pilgrimage,</hi> their tedious and long journeys to viſit the ſhrines of Saints whom they worſhip, alſo their <hi>ſelf-caſtigations,</hi> their whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping &amp; ſcourging of themſelves, conceiving vainly that theſe acts are meritorious, and fancying that they ſhall be juſtified, and ſaved by their works. Thirdly, Be not <hi>Perverſe,</hi> this founds an <hi>alarm</hi> to the <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> the rigid <hi>Antidiſciplinarians,</hi> whom this <hi>long</hi> Name well befits, having continued a <hi>long</hi> time for many
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97025:27"/>years in their opinions, for which they have neither God's Word, nor right reaſon for their Defendants, and from whom there is little or no hope that they will be reclaimed, ſo long as they are guided by their obſtinate wills, which they palliate with the ſpecious &amp; abuſed name of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Their <hi>Sons</hi> begot by them, and their <hi>Scholars,</hi> the poor <hi>Quakers,</hi> firſt learned of them the Trade of <hi>Separatiſm,</hi> and are (in this of the ſame Temper with them) ſtiffned in <hi>perverſeneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is S Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe l 2. Apol. pro Davide. with others of the Fathers. Iude 19. Exod 22.11.</note> 
               <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> who died a <hi>Convert,</hi> and repented of his vanities, beſpeaks them both (though he be dead) by his lively precept, O vain men, <hi>Be not overmuch righteous,</hi> neither <hi>in doing</hi> that which the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> forbid, (agreeable to the word) <hi>Do not ſeparate,</hi> neither <hi>in not doing</hi> what God allows in his Word, <hi>Do not refuſe to take an Oath,</hi> when there is a great need of it, and when it is required of thee by the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> who is the <hi>Kings</hi> Deputy,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> as he is <hi>God's</hi> vicegerent who commands you to <hi>obey them that have the rule over you,</hi> in things lawful, and ſo you obey them in the Lord, both in reſpect of the <hi>Commander</hi> and the things <hi>Commanded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To that exquiſite gloſs of <hi>Mercerus,</hi> I cannot omit to ſubjoyn another of the great <hi>Scripturist Deodatus</hi> (once <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of <hi>Geneva</hi>) upon the forecited Text of <hi>Eccleſiastes,</hi> which in my opinion comes home to an obſtinate <hi>Quaker,</hi> or any other <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> his numeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal words are theſe. <q>
                  <hi>Be not</hi> bent <hi>too much upon a thing which in thy opinion is</hi> juſt, <hi>without yielding any way either in Charity, or</hi> wiſe <hi>integrity to the opinion of others, to the neceſſity of times, and humane frailty.</hi>
               </q> Surely this holy man would have told an <hi>Anti-juriſt</hi> if he had diſcourſed with him, that he was <hi>overmuch righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous</hi> by his refuſing to <hi>ſwear at all,</hi> and maintaining it to be ſinful in others to ſwear in any caſe, when the ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97025:27"/>jealouſies, frauds, and falſities of men require an <hi>Oath,</hi> or make it neceſſary in <hi>Judicial</hi> proceedings. The ſame <hi>Commentator,</hi> who had an extraordinary gift from God (as his name imports) in expounding the Sacred word, ſays thus in his Comment upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. (The Text which is miſ-interpreted by the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists</hi>) <q>
                  <hi>Seeing that an</hi> Oath <hi>is a means, and an help to Truth, and to proof, appointed by God, and oftentimes very neceſſary, we muſt reſtrain this command of Chriſt</hi> (<hi>to wit,</hi> Swear not at all) <hi>to voluntary Oaths, not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them who have Authority, vain, frivolous and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Oaths, ſeeing thoſe things which are ſet down here have relation onely to ſuch.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be not righteous overmuch</hi> (perverſe <hi>Separatiſt</hi>) <hi>for why ſhouldſt thou deſtroy thy ſelf,</hi> (i.e.) (as <hi>Tremelius</hi> upon the Text) <hi>By thy pride and arrogancy run headlong into deſtruction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col 1.18. Eph. 4.15.</note> by undergoing the penalties of the Laws here, and endangering the ſalvation of thy ſoul hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Separation</hi> from the Church his myſtical <hi>Body,</hi> is a dividing from Chriſt the <hi>Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the laſt place, and for a cloſe of all, I do earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire the <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Abettors</hi> of the <hi>Quaking</hi> party to afford me ſo much Charity, as to believe, that I had no other deſign in undertaking the <hi>Refutation</hi> of their <hi>Treatiſe</hi> (put into my hands by a moſt religious know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſon) but onely their <hi>Conviction,</hi> and <hi>Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For when I had read, what is the ſixth of eleven things which they deſire to be conſidered, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 155, 156, 157.</note> 
               <hi>That their</hi> Refuſal to Swear in all caſes, is a matter of <hi>Faith, and whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> I pitied their miſtake, (as to the former part of their Poſition) and conceived it my duty (with others of the <hi>Clergy</hi>) to undeceive them poor miſtaken ſouls, by demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating that as it is uſual with God, <hi>to ſend men</hi> (as the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97025:28"/>Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>ſtrong deluſions to believe a lye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they received not the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved; ſo They</hi> believe that to be true which is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently falſe, and that it is a ſin to do, what they (though falſly) believe ought not to be done, <hi>(i. e.) To Swear</hi> by the Name of God, although it may be for God's glory in the vindication of the Truth, or to promote a Neighbours good.</p>
            <p>My next deſign was (which is every mans duty) to prevent the <hi>Contagion</hi> which might ſpread amongſt the poor people from their<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.17. Their word will eat as doth a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</note> 
               <hi>Gangreen-Opinion;</hi> for whilſt they profeſs <hi>Conſcience</hi> for their diſobedience, &amp; alledg Scripture (though miſconſtrued) for their <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and colour all with an appearance of outward Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in their lives, not uſually tainted with debauchery, and drunnkeneſs, it may be juſtly feared that the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulacy,</hi> if not fortified by pregnant demonſtrations of Truth againſt their ſpreading errours and Opinions, will cry up their Piety (they appearing for a great part of them morally Juſt, and civilly Innocent, as were ſome of the refined Heathens) and by degrees joyn with them in their Confederacy againſt the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and the <hi>Churche's Conſtitutions,</hi> there being ſown in the hearts of the people the ſeeds of <hi>Rebellion, Faction,</hi> and <hi>Sedition,</hi> which are oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſad effects of <hi>Conventicles,</hi> or <hi>private Meetings,</hi> called by alearned <hi>Greek</hi> Father (from the ſad experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he found of them) <hi>Denns</hi> of <hi>Thieves</hi> or <hi>Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Epiphan.</note> for that the <hi>Meeting-Maſters</hi> ſteal the hearts of Subjects from their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Governors,</hi> of Wives from their Husbands, and of theſe from their Wives, of Children from their Parents, of Servants from their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; for there can be no true love or affection, where there is a difference of Opinion, and Practice, whilſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97025:28"/>two or three of a Family go to <hi>Conventicles,</hi> and the reſt to open <hi>Churches</hi> to joyn with Gods Saints, and Servants in the publick Service of God, as it is enjoyned by the fourth Commandment. He likewiſe terms them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Receptacles of evil Spirits,</hi> ſuch as filled and poſſeſſed the hearts of <hi>Judas,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and may poſſeſs the hearts of many of the <hi>Leaders</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> in them.</p>
            <p>For a <hi>Coronis</hi> or <hi>ſuperpondium</hi> of all hath been writ in the defence of the Legality of a <hi>Judicial,</hi> and in ſome caſes of a <hi>private</hi> Oath, I deſire the <hi>Treatiſt</hi> once more to conſider what he hath ſaid <hi>Pag.</hi> 27. of his <hi>Treatiſe. Take away lying and there remains no more ground for Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> He ſhould have ſaid, there will be no ground for <hi>Perjury;</hi> For ſuppoſe a man never told a <hi>Lye,</hi> yet if an Oath ſhould be required of him by the Magiſtrate to vindicate his own, or anothers ſuſpected Honeſty and Truth, he would have a good ground for his Swearing in this Caſe, he being commanded to do it; ſo that the <hi>Treatiſt</hi>'s Propoſal is vain, as it is likewiſe of a thing that is impoſſible.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11 19.</note> For as <hi>there muſt be Hereſies (i. e.</hi> they cannot be hindred) ſo there will be (as long as the world laſts) <hi>lying,</hi> or falſe-ſpeaking, with diſſimulation amongſt men, <hi>Ergo,</hi> by the <hi>Quakers</hi> own conceſſion, there will be a neceſſity of <hi>Swearing.</hi> Thus I may retort and ſay, the <hi>Anti-Juriſt</hi> is (as the Giant <hi>Goliah</hi> was) wounded with his own weapon,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.51.</note> refuted by his own Argument.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not (out of my tender pity and regard to his Soul, and to the deluded Souls of his Diſciples) leave him gaſping and bleeding under his <hi>wound,</hi> but as I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly praiſed him, and them for their pretended awful reverence to Gods holy Name, ſo (as it becomes a merciful Soul-Phyſician, &amp; as the good <hi>Samaritan</hi> did to the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Traveller, Luke</hi> 10.) I ſhall pour the oyl of my prayers
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97025:29"/>into his <hi>wound,</hi> beſeeching God the Father of mercyes ſo to open his, and the eye of their underſtandings (as he did the eyes of <hi>Balaam</hi>) and the door of their hearts (as he did open <hi>Lydia's</hi>) that they may (laying aſide all prejudice) attend to thoſe ſaving Truths which have been delivered in this <hi>Anti-Treatiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 21.31. Act. 16.14.</note> and (being convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of their errors) ſubmit with a due, and humble <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> (according to the will of God) to the wholſom Laws of the <hi>Realm,</hi> and to the <hi>Churches</hi> laudable conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, that ſo they and we may <hi>meet</hi> now together in love, unity and concord, and hereafter in the <hi>great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> of Heaven above, into which none ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted but only thoſe, who are the true and lively mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Chriſt</hi> their <hi>Head,</hi> who are animated, quickned, and guided by his good Spirit the ſpirit of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>unity,</hi> (which reſts not in the breaſt of a perverſe malicious <hi>Schiſmatick</hi>) and the ſpirit of <hi>Truth,</hi> where with the ſoul of a proud obſtinate <hi>Heretick</hi> (who maintains and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates opinions repugnant to the word of God) is not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned. From that <hi>Venom</hi> of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and this <hi>Peſt</hi> of <hi>Hereſie, Lord</hi> preſerve and defend thy <hi>Church:</hi> And ſo ſanctifie the Hearts, and govern the Tongues of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane <hi>Swearers,</hi> that (being aw'd by a trembling fear of thoſe dreadful Judgments, which have in all ages fallen upon ſuch <hi>miſcreants</hi>) they may with thankful <hi>lips,</hi> and by the holineſs of their <hi>lives</hi> advance thy glory, and publiſh thy praiſes. O let thy <hi>mercy</hi> be glorified in their <hi>Converſion,</hi> and not thy <hi>Juſtice</hi> magnified in their <hi>Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> This I humbly beg in the behalf of them, and all <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> from the Orthodox Profeſſors of thy <hi>Truth,</hi> and ſound <hi>Religion,</hi> for thy mercies ſake and alone merits of thy beloved <hi>Son</hi> our Lord and only Saviour Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97025:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
